Guide to the Otto T. Bannard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Otto Tremont Bannard papers
1871-1929
MS 904
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Correspondence, certificates, photographs, and news clippings relating to Otto T. Bannard's world travels and to his activities as a member of the Yale University Corporation. The most substantive letters are the copies of those written by Bannard to Thomas W. Farnam and other friends between 1921 and 1926 while he was traveling in South America, the Far East, India and Europe. The incoming correspondence is made up chiefly of letters of congratulation on Bannard's fundraising activities for Yale and on his appointment as school commissioner of New York. Also included is correspondence on a portrait of Robert J. Cook for Yale University, together with a photograph of Cook and of Bannard.
Bannard, Otto Tremont, 1854-1929
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of A. C. Downing, 1942, and Carl A. Lohmann, 1948.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of papers pertaining to Otto Tremont Bannard, in particular to his world travels and his activities as member of the Yale University Corporation. Included are correspondence, certificates, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
Bannard's outgoing correspondence consists of typed copies of letters written to Thomas W. Farnam and other friends while Bannard was traveling in South America, the Far East, India, and Europe, between 1921 and 1926. His letters discuss local economic conditions and politics and customs, and his own social activities while traveling. There are also a number of letters written from the United States; these contain comments on Yale Corporation business as well as other matters. Bannard's incoming correspondence consists largely of letters of thanks and congratulations from a variety of friends and associates, but also included are letters from the Yale Corporation thanking Bannard for his work as national chairman of the endowment campaign, and letters of appointment as school commissioner in New York City. A few of the letters also deal with a portrait of Robert Johnstone Cook for Yale University. Photographs of Cook and the portrait are included in this collection.
Other materials in the collection include a genealogy of the Bannard family compiled by Bannard, newspaper clippings about him, and two resolutions on the occasion of his death. A copy of the prayer offered at Bannard's funeral by Henry Sloane Coffin is included with the letters to Thomas W. Farnam, which are contained in a bound volume.
The volume of letters to Thomas W. Farnam were donated to Yale University by Carl A. Lohmann in 1948; the other papers were donated in 1942 by A. C. Downing.
Biographical / Historical
Otto Tremont Bannard was born in Brooklyn, New York, on April 28, 1854. He graduated from Yale University in 1876, with the degree of B.A. In 1878, he received an LL.B. from Columbia University and in 1924, he received an LL.D. from Colgate University. In the decade after his graduation from Columbia, Bannard remained in New York City while practicing law. He was director, trustee, or president of numerous banking and insurance companies and ran for mayor of New York City in 1909. Bannard died in 1929.
Asia; Europe -- Description and travel; Bankers; Bannard, Otto Tremont, 1854-1929; Cook, Robert Johnston, 1849-1922; Farnam, Thomas Wells, 1877-1943; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale Corporation
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing
      - Letters to unidentified correspondents, 1921, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Letters to Thomas W. Farnam, 1923-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Incoming
      - Brannell, Clark W., 1909 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Charity Organization Society, 1928 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Cutten, George P., 1924 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Depew, Chauncey M., 1926 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Niemeyer, John H., 1924 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Root, Elihu, 1909 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Schiff, Jacob H., 1909 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Seymour, George Dudley, 1924 August 21, September 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Taft, William Howard, 1927 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Yale University, 1928 February 11, 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters of appointment as Commissioner of Common Schools, New York City, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "History of the Family Surnamed... Bannard", 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Resolutions on the death of Otto T. Bannard
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1929 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Yale Club of New York City, [1929?] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Robert Johnstone Cook, 1871, [1912?] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)